Preliminary Guide to the Southerners on New Ground records, 1993-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Southerners on New Ground records 1993-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Southerners on New Ground
7200 items 9.6 linear feet
According to the organization's website, Southerners on New Ground (SONG) currently works to build, connect, and sustain those in the South who believe in liberation across all lines of race, class, culture, gender and sexuality, through a membership of 600 primarily LGBT people.
The accession (2009-0098) (7200 items; 9.6 lin. ft.; dated 1993-2004) includes administrative and financial records, programming materials, and organizational files, all stemming from retreats, training, workshops, and community events sponsored or promoted by SONG. The accession also includes SONG materials from the Bayard Rustin project, People of Color activities, Pride at Work, and the Highlander Economy Educational Institute, among others. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Gift, 2009 (2009-0098), 9.6 lin. ft.
Biographical / Historical Note
Southerners on New Ground (SONG) was established in 1994 following a 1993 National Gay and Lesbian Task Force conference that brought black and white lesbians together in an effort to unite LGBT communities with racial minorities, particularly African Americans, against discrimination by conservative, right-wing groups. SONG attempts to provide a regional infrastructure for LGBT organizing through retreats, training workshops, meetings, and other community outreach programs. The organization is based in Durham, North Carolina, with offices in Atlanta. It currently has a membership of about 600 primarily LGBT people.
Collection Overview
The accession (2009-0098) (7200 items; 9.6 lin. ft.; dated 1993-2004) includes administrative and financial records, programming materials, and organizational files, all stemming from retreats, training, workshops, and community events sponsored or promoted by SONG. The accession also includes SONG materials from the Bayard Rustin project, People of Color activities, Pride at Work, and the Highlander Economy Educational Institute, among others. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Homosexuality -- Southern States
Discrimination -- Southern States
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Southerners on New Ground
United States -- Social conditions -- 1990-
Videotapes
DVDs
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2009-0098), 1993-2004, (7 boxes)
  The accession (2009-0098) (7200 items; 9.6 lin. ft.; dated 1993-2004) includes administrative and financial records, programming materials, and organizational files, all stemming from retreats, training, workshops, and community events sponsored or promoted by SONG. The accession also includes SONG materials from the Bayard Rustin project, People of Color activities, Pride at Work, and the Highlander Economy Educational Institute, among others. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
  This is an unprocessed addition to this collection. Materials have not been arranged beyond their original condition, and folder titles may not accurately reflect folder contents. Please consult Research Services if you have any questions.
  - Programs and workshop evaluations, 1996-2001 (Box 1)
    - Pride at Work
    - Dismantling Internalized Homophobia
    - Level Playing Field
    - People of Color
    - Beyond White Guilt
    - Broadening the We
  - Town meetings, 1997
  - Organizational early work, 1994
  - Highlander Economic Education Institute
  - Poor People's Movement, 1998
  - Regional Economic Justice Network (REJN)
  - Organizational files, A-N
  - Workshops (Box 2)
    - Higher Ground, 2000
    - WomonWrites, 1995
  - Retreats
    - Atlanta, 1994
    - Women's Retreat, 2000-2001
    - Retreat summary logs
    - People of Color Retreat, 1997-1998, 2000
    - Allies Retreat, 1998
    - Cultural Worker Retreat, 1996-1999
  - Mapping Project
  - Printed materials
  - SONG conferences and programs, 2003
    - NC Unity Conference
    - Black Solidarity
    - Durham/NCCU Now
    - Training Conference
    - SC Pride Conference
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1998
  - Bylaws
  - Membership information
  - Personnel policies
  - Akers, David B.
  - Direct Appeals
  - Southern retreat locations
  - Advertisements
  - Videotapes (2)
  - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force (NGLTF) (Box 3)
    - People of Color (POC) Planning Committee
    - Creating Change, 2000-2001
  - National Organizers Alliance (NOA), 2001
  - National Black Gay and Lesbians (NBGL) Forum
  - Organizational files, N-Z
  - South Africa, 1999
  - Rustin Project
    - Program
    - Applications
    - Retreat
    - Evaluations
    - Durham
    - Atlanta
    - New Orleans
    - Louisville
  - SONG Training curricula materials (Box 4)
  - Bayard Rustin Project materials, 2001
  - Florida Coalition Against Domestic Violence training materials, 2001
  - SONG logos
  - Correspondence, 1994-2001
  - Hate mail
  - Program files, 1993-2001
  - Printed materials
  - IRS communications, 1999
  - Emergency Conference and Project South, 2001
  - Administrative files, 2002
    - Brochures
    - Staff meetings
    - Move information
    - Bulletin board
  - SONG 10th Anniversary, 2004
  - To Do folders, 2003
  - Administrative files, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Administrative files, 2000s (Box 6)
  - Fundraising
  - Outreach
  - Bayard Rustin project
  - Organizational development and marketing
  - Samples
  - Videotapes (15) (Box 7)
    - In the Name of Justice Seminar, Tape 1-3, 2004
    - In the Name of Justice Seminar, Tape 4-7, 2004
    - Gay Cuba, 1995
    - A Gay and Lesbian Speak Out
    - From the Mountains to the Maquiladoras
    - SONG Retreat
    - Free Speech TV
      - And Justice For All PSA Intro/Outro Tape
      - And Justice For All Clip Tape
      - And Justice For All sample tapes Nos. 1, 2, 4-7, 9
  - DVD (1)
    - SONG 15th video